Finding aid for Ruth Ellis papers, 1910-2000 0047 Aa 2 Ac
Bentley Historical Library
Ruth Ellis papers
1910-2000
1997-2000
Bentley Historical Library
Ellis, Ruth, 1899-2000
0047 Aa 2 Ac
2.5 linear feet
3.6 GB online
Ruth Ellis of Detroit, Michigan was well known in the Gay community as the oldest known African American Lesbian. She was a business woman, owned a printing company, and held social gatherings at her home at a time when there were few opportunities for Gay African Americans to gather. During the last twenty years of her life she was active in the Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, and Transgender community and in the Senior Citizens movement. The collection contains correspondence, photographs, and publications.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Collection received from Ruth Ellis (donor no. 8774 ) in 2000.
Accruals
No further additions to the papers are expected.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open to research.
Existence and Location of Copies
Digitization: The Library has undertaken the digitization of a number of sound recordings within this collection. The resulting audio files are available for playback only in the Bentley Library Reading Room. Links to item images and additional information are available within this finding aid. Original sound recordings are only available for staff use.
Biographical / Historical
Ruth Ellis was born on July 23, 1899 in Springfield Illinois, the youngest of four children born to Charles and Carrie Ellis. After the death of her mother, Ellis and her brothers were raised by her father. At age 37, she moved to Detroit and was soon joined by her partner, Cicilene "Babe" Franklin also of Springfield. The couple stayed together for more than thirty years, during which time they bought a home on Oakland Avenue and opened a small print shop, the Ellis and Franklin Printing Company.
During the late 1930s and 1940s the Ellis/Franklin house served as a meeting place and temporary shelter for Gay men and Lesbians. Ms. Ellis ran the print shop until her retirement at age 65. She actively participated in the events of the Lesbian community nation-wide until her death in 2000 at the age of 101.
Scope and Contents
The Ruth Ellis collection contains correspondence, photographs, and publications related to Ms. Ellis's life and her activities in the Gay and Lesbian community. The papers are arranged in the following series: Papers, Correspondence, and Events; Photographs; and Miscellaneous Materials.
Lesbians -- Michigan -- Detroit.; African American lesbians -- Michigan -- Detroit.; African Americans -- Michigan -- Detroit.; African Americans -- Michigan -- Detroit.; African American lesbians -- Michigan -- Detroit.; Lesbians -- Michigan -- Detroit.; Printers.; Printing press.; Photographs.; Ellis, Ruth, 1899-2000; Ellis, Ruth, 1899-2000; Ellis family.
- Papers, Correspondence, and Events
  Scope and Contents
  The Papers, Correspondence, and Events series holds biographical information; email, letters, and cards; newspaper clippings; and publicity materials. A cassette recording and partial transcript of "Living on Earth," a National Public Radio broadcast with Ruth Ellis, is included, as well as materials related to the film "Living with Pride: Ruth Ellis @100."
  - Awards and citations (Box 1)
  - Biographical information (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Letters, cards, postcards, 1989-2000 (Box 1)
    - Email messages, 1998-2000 (Box 1)
  - Events
    - 100th birthday celebration, 1999 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous events, 1984-2000 (Box 1)
  - Golden Threads, publications for older Lesbians, 1998-1999 (Box 1)
  - "Living with Pride: Ruth Ellis @100," film reviews and publicity, 1999-2000 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (drawings, contact lists, fliers) (Box 1)
  - Publicity, magazines, and newspaper clippings, 1998-2000 (Box 2)
  - Yearbook, Springfield High School, 1918-1919 (Box 2)
- Audio Recording
  Conditions Governing Access
  Digitized audio files are currently available only in the Bentley Historical Library reading room on designated Bentley Library computers.
  - "Living on Earth," National Public Radio broadcast with Ruth Ellis, 2000 January 07; Audio Cassette, Compact Cassette, 1 7/8 ips (Box 1)
    - [Side 1], 0047-SR-1-1; mp3 file; Series of radio programs entitled: "Welcome To The Future: It's Warm", "Cleaner School Buses", "Nikitin Freed", and "Buffalo Hunt." partila transicrpt available
    - [Side 2], 0047-SR-1-2; mp3 file; Series of radio programs entitled: "Welcome To The Future: It's Warm", "Cleaner School Buses", "Nikitin Freed", and "Buffalo Hunt."
- Photographs
  The Photographs series contains snapshots and photo albums of Ms Ellis's family, friends, and events in the Gay community. There are several photographs of Ruth and her family members in their youth, her home in Springfield, Illinois, and her printing press.
  - Family
    - Undated (Box 2)
    - Before, 1960 (Box 2)
  - General, 1950s-2000; 11 folders (Box 2)
  - General, undated; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Photo albums
    - 86th birthday (Box 3)
    - 90th birthday (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous, 4 Volumes (Box 3)
- Miscellaneous
  Miscellaneous Materials contains a book, "Respecting the Soul: Daily Reflections for Black Lesbians and Gays," dedicated to Ms. Ellis; several guest books for her birthday celebrations, and a journal.
  - Guest books
    - 90th birthday, 1989 (Box 3)
    - 93rd birthday, 1992 (Box 3)
    - 100th birthday, 1999 (Box 3)
  - Journal, 1997 (Box 3)
  - "Respecting the Soul: Daily Reflections for Black Lesbians and Gays," by K. Boykin, dedicated to Ruth Ellis, 1999 (Box 3)